<?xml version="1.0"?>
<BOOK
><BOOKINFO
><TITLE
>The chaos Coding Standards</TITLE><AUTHORGROUP
><AUTHOR
><FIRSTNAME
>Per</FIRSTNAME><SURNAME
>Lundberg</SURNAME></AUTHOR></AUTHORGROUP><PUBDATE
>$Id$</PUBDATE></BOOKINFO><PREFACE
><TITLE
>Introduction</TITLE><PARA
>      This is The chaos Coding Standards. It is a guide in programming
      for the chaos operating system. If you intend to submit your
      code, please adhere to these standards. This will save both you
      and us some unnecessary work reformatting and rewriting the
      code.  It is very important to keep the same quality on all
      code.
    </PARA><PARA
>      The code formatting chapters in this publication is mostly
      C-related, but some of them can be used for other languages too.
    </PARA></PREFACE><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Language choice</TITLE><PARA
>      Choosing the right language for a project is very important. If
      you make a bad choice, it may render the program unusable for
      some, or all, of its users. For example, if you choose a
      language where a free interpreter/compiler is not available, few
      people will be able to use it. So please, choose a language
      which is usable. Another important aspect is to choose a
      language as suitable for the project as possible. For example,
      storm, the chaos kernel, is written in a C and assembly
      combination. This is because those were the most suitable
      languages - C is quite low-level, which is good for a kernel, and
      assembly is almost necessary to use. But those considerations
      may vary depending on your project type. For example, the
      <ABBREV
>cAPS</ABBREV> (chaos Advanced Packaging System) system
      is written in a combination of C and Perl, since we found those
      languages to be most suitable.
   </PARA><PARA
>      If you do not think you will be able to do the project all by
      yourself, try using a language that is widely accepted (C, C++
      and Perl are three good examples). Avoid using "smaller"
      languages like Objective C or Haskell if possible.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>License choice</TITLE><PARA
>      chaos is a free operating system, as defined by the FSF, and as
      such, all parts of it must be free. However, they do not have to
      be GPL, even though we encourage people to release their work
      under this license. This is the list of acceptable licenses for
      chaos:

      <ITEMIZEDLIST
><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            <EMPHASIS
>GNU GPL (General public license)</EMPHASIS> is
            our preferred license for all code we write
            <EMPHASIS
>except</EMPHASIS> for the system
            libraries. This is necessary to make licensing of chaos
            programs under other free licenses possible. Use this
            license if possible.
          </PARA></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            <EMPHASIS
>GNU LGPL (Lesser General Public
            License)</EMPHASIS> permits linkage between your work and
            proprietary (closed-source, non-free) programs. We only
            use this license for the system libraries. It is
            deprecated for everything else.
          </PARA></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            <EMPHASIS
>BSD</EMPHASIS> is the Berkeley Software
            Distribution license. We do not use it, but you may use it
            <EMPHASIS
>if</EMPHASIS>, and only if, you remove the
            advertising clause. We do not recommend using this license
            anyway, since it is not a copyleft and thus does not
            protect your freedom in a way we prefer, but we will
            nevertheless accept if you decide to do so.
          </PARA></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            <EMPHASIS
>The Artistic license</EMPHASIS> is the license
            used by Perl. We do not encourage its usage except for
            Perl-related things; in such cases, please follow the Perl
            example and dual-license your code under both the Artistic
            license and the GNU GPL.
          </PARA></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>	    The GNU FDL (Free Documentation License) is a pretty new
	    license from the Free Software Foundation. It is intended
	    for documentation, and should be used for that.
	  </PARA></LISTITEM></ITEMIZEDLIST>
    </PARA><PARA
>      You do not need to give over the rights to your code to
      us. Licensing it under one of those licenses is probably enough,
      but be careful if you have signed a contract with your employer
      stating they own everything you write. If so, you can not
      legally license the code under GPL yourself. You must get
      permission from your employer to do so. Please be careful with
      these issues so neither you or we get into legal trouble.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Compiler flags</TITLE><PARA
>      The chaos build system, autochaos, automatically uses our
      standard C flags, so there is little need to duplicate them
      here. What our flags do is try to eliminate the pitfalls of the
      C programming language (there are quite a few). The only really
      important flag is -Werror, which turns all warnings into
      errors. We believe this should have been the default in gcc. A
      warning is nothing to take lightly. And really, if you do not
      care about the warning, why don't you turn it off?
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Symbol names</TITLE><PARA
>      All symbol names should be in lower-case only. The only
      exception to this is acronyms like VGA, GDT, IDT etc, where you
      could put the acronym in uppercase if you would like. Separate
      logic words with underscores, like this: screen_base_address.
    </PARA><PARA
>      It is very important to be consequent when naming your
      functions, variables and such. Do not abbreviate names. It only
      makes it harder to figure out what a function or variable is
      used for. Symbol names must <EMPHASIS
>always</EMPHASIS> be
      descriptive. One-name variables are neat for the lazy, but is a
      no-no. Try to name your counter variables index (if you are
      operating on a one-dimensional list), x and y (if a
      two-dimensional structure), x, y and z, and so on. In short, try
      to be as descriptive as possible. It is tempting at times to
      call your variables i, j, k and such, but this just makes the
      program more difficult for other people to get into.
    </PARA><PARA
>      All global symbols should have their file name prepended to
      them. Thus, all the symbols exported from the file
      <FILENAME
MOREINFO="NONE"
>port.c</FILENAME> should be named port_*. When doing a
      library, it is okay to split it up into smaller files and still
      have the functions named foo_bar. (if the library name is foo)
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Functions</TITLE><PARA
>      The usage of functions is standard in all structured
      programming. You should try to keep your functions as long as
      suitable. We do not give a specific limit, but try to split your
      code in natural functions. For example, if your program is
      reading and processing lines from a file, and the processing is
      more than a few statements of code, put it in a separate
      function. This is not really difficult when you get used to it.
    </PARA><PARA
>      Always put a comment before the function declaration where you
      state what it does. It is also desirable that you document the
      input and return variables if it is not implicit.
    </PARA><PARA
>      A typical function declaration can look like this:
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      /* Initialise the page allocation system. */
      
      void page_init (void)
      {
        [...]
      }
    </PROGRAMLISTING><PARA
>      As you see, we do not put the function name in the leftmost
      column. There is no reason to do so. It just makes the code look
      ugly.
    </PARA><PARA
>      Also, if the function types and names do not fit on one line,
      write it like this:
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      extern inline return_type system_call_thread_control
        (process_id_type process_id, u32 class, u32 parameter)
    </PROGRAMLISTING></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Comments</TITLE><PARA
>      Code without comments is like an operating system without
      applications -- it is not very usable. Try to comment your code
      as much as suitable to understand it for a reasonably
      experienced programmer. A good idea is to let someone else look
      at your code and see where she gets stuck.
    </PARA><PARA
>      Always put comments on their own line, with a blank line above
      and below. Do not put comments at the end of the line, after the
      code; it just makes everything messy.
    </PARA><PARA
>      When commenting a statement, put the comment above the
      statement, like this:
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      /* Check if we are ready yet. */

      if (finished ())
      {
        return;
      }
      </PROGRAMLISTING><PARA
>      Some people like C++ comments. We prefer to only use them for
      temporary commenting away code, so that they can not get
      mistaken for being real comments.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Indentation</TITLE><PARA
>      The indentation level should be two spaces. Do not use
      tabs. When starting a new block, the braces should be on their own line
      at the same level of indentation as the previous line, like this:
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      if (age &gt; LEGAL_AGE)
      {
        print_age (age);
      }
    </PROGRAMLISTING></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Inline assembly</TITLE><PARA
>      Inline assembly is a twin-edged sword. It can make
      computing-intensive programs a lot speedier, at the cost of
      making the source more difficult to get into. Generally, only
      use it if the speed gain is significant, or in the kernel and
      other places where things might be impossible to do without
      it. In general user programs there is little need for it, but
      occasionally, it might be okay. The thumb rule is to start by
      optimising the algorithms. If that is not enough, try to profile
      your code and see where the most time is spent, and rewrite
      those parts in assembly. If the gain is more than a few percent,
      inline assembly is okay.
    </PARA><PARA
>      If you for one reason or another have to use inline assembly, do
      it like this:
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      asm volatile
      ("\
        pushl %2
        pushl %3
        pushl %4
        lcall %5, $0
      "
      : "=a" (return_value), "=g" (*buffer)
      : "g" (buffer), "g" (parameter), "g" (class),
        "n" (SYSTEM_CALL_KERNELFS_ENTRY_READ &lt;&lt; 3));
    </PROGRAMLISTING><PARA
>      Do not write long blocks of uncommented inline assembly, but
      keep it into functional blocks separated with blank lines and
      comments, so it is easier to get into the code.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Miscellaneous</TITLE><PARA
>      Here you will find stuff that did not fit into one of the
      previous chapters:

      <ITEMIZEDLIST
><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            When writing if-statements, always use braces to indicate
            a block, even for one-line statements where it is not
            required. Like this:
          </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>            if (age &gt; LEGAL_AGE)
            {
              print_age (age);
            }
            else
            {
              return;
            }
          </PROGRAMLISTING></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            When writing switch statements, always use braces in the
            case blocks. Like this:
          </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>            switch (key)
            {
              case ESCAPE:
              {
                return;
              }
            }
          </PROGRAMLISTING></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>            When writing conditional statements, never use the fact
            that non-zero is TRUE. You can only do this on
            booleans. If something is not a boolean, you must compare
            it with a number. Like this:
          </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>            if (get_age () != 0)
            {
              do_something ();
            }
          </PROGRAMLISTING><PARA
>            This makes things much clearer. The lack of real booleans
            in C is showing, but using this fact makes your programs
            very ugly.
          </PARA></LISTITEM><LISTITEM
><PARA
>	    When declaring external functions (in library header files
	    and elsewhere), always write like this:
	  </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>	    extern my_function (void);
	  </PROGRAMLISTING><PARA
>	    The extern attribute is not mandatory in gcc, but use it
	    anyway since it makes it very clear what we are talking about.
	  </PARA></LISTITEM></ITEMIZEDLIST>
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Whitespace</TITLE><PARA
>      A lot of programmers tend to forget how important whitespace is
      to write good code. A good example of this can be found in the
      Linux source code, but unfortunately, the practice is rather
      common (especially in the Unix world). In chaos, we use as much
      whitespace as is practical. Always use whitespace between
      function names and parentheses, after commas, semicolons and
      other places. Separate blocks of code with blank lines and
      comments.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><CHAPTER
><TITLE
>Documentation</TITLE><PARA
>      Documentation is essential for a program to succeed. All
      documentation should be written in English (but may also be
      translated to other languages if desirable). The standard format
      for documentation in chaos is SGML using the DocBook DTD. You
      can find more information about this DTD on
      the <ULINK
URL="http://www.docbook.org"
>DocBook Web Site</ULINK>.
    </PARA></CHAPTER><APPENDIX
><TITLE
>Examples</TITLE><EXAMPLE
><TITLE
>A C example</TITLE><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>/* $Id$ */
/* Abstract: Semaphores for the kernel. */

/* Copyright 1999-2000 chaos development. */

/* This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
   modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as
   published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the
   License, or (at your option) any later version.

   This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
   WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
   MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
   General Public License for more details.

   You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
   along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
   Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307
   USA */

#include &lt;storm/i386/error_numbers.h&gt;
#include &lt;storm/i386/semaphore.h&gt;
#include &lt;storm/i386/thread.h&gt;
#include &lt;storm/i386/types.h&gt;
#include &lt;storm/state.h&gt;

/* Semaphore lock variable. 1 if none is accessing the semaphores, 0
   if someone is. */

static kernel_mutex_type semaphore_mutex = 1;

error_type semaphore_wait (kernel_semaphore_type *semaphore)
{
  spin_lock (semaphore_mutex);

  if (*semaphore &lt;= 0)
  {
    spin_unlock (semaphore_mutex);
    thread_block_semaphore (STATE_SEMAPHORE, semaphore);
    return ERROR_UNKNOWN;
  }
  else
  {
    (*semaphore)--;
    spin_unlock (semaphore_mutex);
  }
  
  return ERROR_UNKNOWN;
}

/* Release the lock around the given semaphore. */

error_type semaphore_signal (kernel_semaphore_type *semaphore)
{
  spin_lock (semaphore_mutex);

  if (thread_unblock_semaphore (semaphore) == ERROR_NO_THREAD_UNBLOCKED)
  {
    (*semaphore)++;
  }

  spin_unlock (semaphore_mutex);

  return ERROR_UNKNOWN;
}
      </PROGRAMLISTING></EXAMPLE><EXAMPLE
><TITLE
>A Perl example</TITLE><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>#!/usr/bin/perl -w

# $Id$

# Abstract: Program for building chaos packages.
# Author: Per Lundberg &lt;plundis@chaosdev.org&gt;

use chaos::cAPS;
use strict;

my $CONFIGFILE;

# Abstract: Clean things up.

sub cleanup
{
  close (CONFIGFILE);
}

my $cAPS = new chaos::cAPS ('/mnt/chaos/system/caps');
my %config_keyword = $cAPS-&gt;config_keyword_get ();
my %config;

# All mandatory keywords are stored in this list.

my @mandatory_keyword = ('name', 'type', 'version', 'description' );

open (CONFIGFILE, '&lt;chaos/config') or die "Couldn't open chaos/config.\n";

# This is the main config file parser loop. Neat, isn't it? :) This
# used to be written in flex/bison, and was rather complex and
# difficult to get into. But now...

while (&lt;CONFIGFILE&gt;)
{
  chop;
  ($_, my $dummy) = split ('#');
  (my $key, my $value) = /^([\w\-]+)\s*=\s*\"([^\"]*)\"/;

  if (!$key || !$value)
  {
    print ("Syntax error in config file: $_.\n");
    exit;
  }
  
  my $flag = 1;

  foreach my $config_key (keys %config_keyword)
  {
    if ($config_keyword{$config_key} eq $key)
    {
      $config{$key} = $value;
      $flag = 0;
    }
  }
  if ($flag == 1)
  {
    print ("Bad keyword '$key' in config file. Aborting.\n");
    exit 1;
  }
}

# It's time to start some serious business. But first, we check that
# all mandatory keywords have been specified.

foreach my $keyword (@mandatory_keyword)
{
  if (!$config{$keyword})
  {
    print ("Mandatory keyword $keyword missing from config file.\n");
    exit 1;
  }
}

# All things clear? Great! Now we check if the package directory
# exists.

# ..chaos/$config{name}

# Clean things up.

cleanup ();
      </PROGRAMLISTING></EXAMPLE></APPENDIX><APPENDIX
><TITLE
>Emacs settings for chaos indentation</TITLE><PARA
>      This is our .emacs settings for chaos indentation style for C
      code. It makes writing compliant code much easier.
    </PARA><PROGRAMLISTING
FORMAT="LINESPECIFIC"
>      
      ;; chaos indentation style
      
      (defconst chaos-c-style 
       '(
         (c-basic-offset . 2)
         (c-comment-only-line-offset . (0 . 0))
         (c-comment-continuation-stars . "")
         (c-hanging-comment-ender-p . t)
         (c-offsets-alist . (
           (statement-block-intro . +)
           (knr-argdecl-intro . +)
           (substatement-open . 0)
           (label . 0)
           (statement-cont . +)
           (case-label . 2)
         )
        )
       )
       "chaos"
      )
      
      (defun chaos-c-mode-common-hook ()
      
      ;; add my personal style and set it for the current buffer
      
      (c-add-style "chaos" chaos-c-style t)
      
      ;; this will make sure spaces are used instead of tabs
      
      (setq indent-tabs-mode nil))
      
      (add-hook 'c-mode-common-hook 'chaos-c-mode-common-hook)
    </PROGRAMLISTING></APPENDIX></BOOK>
