<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD DocBk XML V3.1.7//EN"
               "/usr/lib/sgml/dtd/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd">

<book>
  <bookinfo>
    
    <title>Installation of chaos</title>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Per</firstname>
        <surname>Lundberg</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <pubdate>$Id$</pubdate>
  </bookinfo>
    
  <preface>
    <title>Introduction</title>
       
    <para>
      chaos is, as you probably know, an operating system written
      totally from scratch by a bunch of Swedish (and others)
      hackers. Right now, we have not come as far as to write an
      installation program, so getting chaos onto your computer is not
      as straightforward as it could be. In this paper, you will be
      able to get some information about the different methods of
      setting things up. Hopefully, after reading this, you will find
      setting chaos up pretty trivial. In any way, please do not
      hesitate to mail staff@chaosdev.org if this information is wrong
      in any way.
    </para>

    <para>
      Now, as you will see, there are several methods of trying out
      chaos. They have one chapter each, and are listed in order of
      complexity.
    </para>
    
  </preface>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Installing a floppy image</title>

    <para>
      Using a floppy image to try out chaos is very easy. All you have
      to do is download the floppy image (from our download page on
      http://www.chaosdev.org, or via anonymous FTP from
      ftp://ftp.chaosdev.org/chaos). Now, gunzip it if your web browser did
      not do it auto-magically (Netscape Navigator does that, and
      possible others too). If you do not have a program for
      decompressing gz files, get one from
      ftp://ftp.gnu.org/pub/gnu/gzip.
    </para>

    <para>
      When you have decompressed the floppy image, get it onto a 1.44
      3,5" floppy. If you are using DOS or Windows, get the
      rawrite2.exe program from ftp://ftp.chaosdev.org/dosutils. Write
      like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      rawrite2 -f floppy.img -d a:
    </screen>

    <para>
      (Give the floppy image a letter within the 8.3 range to avoid
      problems; rawrite is a DOS program with no support for long file
      names.)
    </para>

    <para>
      If you are using some kind of Unix (most probably Linux or some
      of the BSD systems. Anything else is probably out of the scope
      of this document, and if you are using such a system, you should
      be skilled enough to do such things anyway), do like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      dd if=floppy.image of=/dev/fd0
    </screen>

    <para>
      If using BSD-derived systems, you will need to use /dev/fd0c
      instead. Anyway, that is all! Now, boot a computer with this
      floppy, and something magic will (hopefully) appear. Much joy!
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Compiling the source</title>

    <para>
      Do you feel tired of waiting for us to update the floppy images,
      or do you feel to do some chaos hacking? If so, compiling the
      source is probably of interest. It is really not very
      difficult. First, get the sources, and decompress them. Do
      something like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      tar xvIf chaos_snapshot-20001224.tar.bz2
    </screen>

    <para>
      (You must have a pretty recent GNU tar and a working bzip2 for
      this to work. If you are using an older version of tar, you
      might have to decompress the file manually first. Read the man
      pages for your bzip2 and tar programs for more information.)
    </para>

    <para>
      Now, go to the newly created chaos directory, and read the file
      README.Linux. It will contain up-to-date instructions for
      building the system.
    </para>

    <para>
      If everything works out fine, your chaos root (/mnt/chaos is the
      only possible choice right now -- sorry about that) will be
      filled with new, fresh stuff. It is not really more difficult
      than this.
    </para>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title>Net-booting</title>

    <para>
      The absolutely most elegant way to boot chaos, especially when
      developing the system, is to use the net-boot feature of GNU
      GRUB, our boot loader. It is a little tricky to get up, so we
      provide some information for your pleasure.
    </para>

    <para>
      This chapter will tell you how to get GNU GRUB with net-boot
      installed on a floppy, but you should be able to do the same if
      you want to install GNU GRUB on your hard drive. The reason we
      are primarily focusing on doing a floppy is because it is
      easier, and it will make most people happy. In the future, it is
      very likely that we will extend this appendix to include
      information about installating onto hard drives too.
    </para>

    <para>
      First, you must choose which method you want to use to configure
      the IP address of the system you want to net-boot on (hereafter
      referred to as the client). This is used to select which
      software to install on the machine you want to boot from
      (hereafter called the server). The methods available in GNU GRUB
      right now are rarpd, bootp and DHCP. They all work pretty
      similarly, so if you are unsure of which one to choose, just
      pick anyone. If you happen to be on a network where a DHCP or
      bootp server already exists, you can be a little tricky and
      install a rarpd server, without risk of interfering with the
      other server. (You can find all the software you need for this
      at http://www.freshmeat.net/)
    </para>

    <para>
      When you have got the IP configuration server up and running, it
      is time to install a TFTP server. TFTP is an acronym for Trivial
      File Transfer Protocol and is used by GNU GRUB to transfer the
      kernel and servers from the boot server. You can find TFTP
      servers at the same place as the rest of the software.
    </para>

    <para>
      (I will not go into detail about how to configure the software
      here, but I will just mention one thing I would like you to
      avoid: GNU GRUB does not support "IP ranges" in the DHCP server
      configuration. You must have a host entry for the machine in
      question).
    </para>

    <para>
      Okay, so you might have succeeded in getting rarpd/bootpd/dhcpd
      and tftpd installed, but where do we go from here? This is
      where it starts getting interesting. Unpack the GNU GRUB source,
      change to the newly created directory and write like this:
    </para>
    
    <screen>
      ./configure --help | less
    </screen>

    <para>
      Now, make sure your network adapter is supported by GRUB. If it
      is, run configure again, with the correct parameter. For
      example, like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      ./configure --enable-rtl8139
    </screen>

    <para>
      Now, run the 'make', which will compile the GRUB stage1 and
      stage2 files. For information about how to install the created
      files, check the GNU GRUB documentation. Basically, format the
      floppy (FAT or ext2 is just fine) and copy the stage1 and stage2
      files there. Now, run the GRUB shell and write something like
      this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      install (fd0)/stage1 (fd0) (fd0)/stage2 (fd0)/menu
    </screen>

    <para>
      Now, create a file on the floppy, called menu. It should look
      like this:
    </para>

    <screen>
      timeout = 1
      title = Netboot
      dhcp
      configfile (nd)/mnt/chaos/config/grub/menu
    </screen>

    <para>
      Substitute dhcp with bootp or rarp if you like. Now, boot with
      this floppy, and it will (hopefully) configure its IP address
      and load the second configuration file from the server.
    </para>
  </appendix>

  <appendix>
    <title>Example GNU GRUB menu file</title>
    <para>
      This is what I use on my net-boot server:
    </para>

    <screen>
timeout = 2

title Net-chaos
root (nd)
kernel /mnt/chaos/system/kernel/storm
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/keyboard
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/vga
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/console
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/log
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/cluido
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/cluido
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/cluido
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/cluido
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/initial_ramdisk
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/fat
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/virtual_file_system
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/pci
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/serial
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/boot
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/tornado
    </screen>

    <para>
      This is what I use when booting chaos locally:
    </para>

    <screen>
title chaos
root (hd0,2)
kernel /mnt/chaos/system/kernel/storm
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/keyboard
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/console
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/vga
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/cluido
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/log
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/idle
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/fat
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/initial_ramdisk
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/virtual_file_system
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/ipv4
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/3c509
module /mnt/chaos/system/servers/boot
    </screen>
  </appendix>
</book>